A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of Administration, Correspondence and Subject Files, 1994-1998
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1994-1998
The Library of Virginia
35870
2 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia. Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 35870 was transfered from the Office of the Secretary of Administration, by Arlene Smith, on 19 June 1998, to the Library of Virginia for permanent retention.
Biographical Information
The Office of Administration was established in 1966 as part of the Office of the Governor to assist the chief executive in carrying out his duties. Several agencies including the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Building and Planning reported to the Commissioner of Administration. This system was inadequate. In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. The Office of Administration was made one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Administration was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed T. Edward Temple, the Commissioner of Administration since 1970, as the first Secretary of Administration. When Temple took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Buildings, Automated Data Processing, Justice and Crime Prevention, State Planning and Community Affairs, Council on the Environment, State Board of Elections and the Office of Special Programs. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since 1972. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature combined the secretariats for administration and finance, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were separated. The Secretary of Administration is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. Currently, the Secretary of Administration is responsible for the direction or jurisdiction over the following state agencies and boards: Department of Charitable Gaming, Compensation Board, State Board of Elections, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Public Broadcasting Board, and the Department of Veterans Services.
T. Edward Temple, the first Secretary of Administration, announced in August 1973 that he was leaving state service effective January 1974. In December 1973, Governor-elect Mills E. Godwin, Jr., announced the appointment of Maurice B. Rowe, III, as Secretary of Administration. Rowe had served as Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Holton administration. On July 1, 1976, the secretariates of administration and finance were combined. Rowe served until the end of the Godwin administration in January 1978 when he became Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Dalton administration. In December 1977 Governor-elect John N. Dalton picked Charles B. Walker, the state comptroller, as Secretary of Administration and Finance. The office wielded great influence and authority under Walker who was known as the "Little Governor". Walker resigned in June 1981 to become a vice-president for Ethyl Corporation. Stuary Connock, state budget and planning director, served as Secretary of Administration and Finance until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982.
Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Wayne F. Anderson, a former Alexandria city manager, Secretary of Administration and Finance. Anderson announced his resignation in May 1984 to join the faculty of George Mason University. His resignation was prompted by a cabinet reorganization to take effect on July 1, 1984 which divided the Secretary of Administration and Finance into separate secretariats and combined the secretariats of transportation and public safety. Governor Robb appointed Secretary of Transportation Andrew B. Fogarty as new Secretary of Administration. Fogarty served until June 1985 when he became Sectretary of Transportation and Public Safety following the resignation of Franklin E. White. David K. McCloud, Robb's chief of staff, assumed the duties of Secretary of Administration for the remainder of Robb's term.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles chose Carolyn J. Moss, head of the Office of Minority Business Enterprise under Governor Robb, as Secretary of Administration. Moss served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. Governor-elect L. Douglas Wilder appointed Ruby G. Martin, a Richmond attorney, as Secretary of Administration. In January 1994 Governor-elect George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed his campaign manager, Michael E. Thomas, Secretary of Administration. Thomas served until the end of Allen's term in January 1998. Governor James S. Gilmore appointed Thomas Deputy Secretary of Technology in August 1998. In January 1998 Governor-elect James S. Gilmore III named G. Bryan Slater as Secretary of Administration. Slater also served as Gilmore's Deputy Chief of Staff. He worked on Gilmore's campaign for attorney general in 1993 and served as his director of administration when Gilmore was Virginia Attorney General (1994-1997). Slater resigned in March 2001 to work for the Republican National Committee which Gilmore chaired. He was replaced by his deputy, Donald L. Moseley who served until the end of the Gilmore administration in January 2002.
Governor-elect Mark R. Warner selected Sandra Bowen as Secretary of Administration in January 2002. Bowen had previously served as Special Assistant to Governor Charles S. Robb, and as Secretary of the Commonwealth during the administration of Governor Gerald L. Baliles. She was also the Director of Gubernatorial Transition between the Robb and Baliles administrations. Secretary Bowen served under Governor Warner for his entire term, and was replaced in 2006 when Governor-elect Timothy Kaine selected Viola Baskerville as his Secretary of Administration.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of: Correspondence with Secretary of Administration Agencies, Governor's Working Papers, Correspondence with other Secretariats, Subject Files, General Assembly and Legislative Studies.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1994-1998., Extent: 2 cu. ft (2 boxes). (Box 1-2)
  The originial arrangement of the organization has been maintained.
  - Charitable Gaming Commission, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charitable Gaming Commission - Spring NAGRA Conference, 1995. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commonwealth Competition Council, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Compensation Board, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Elections, State Board of, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Employee Relations Counselors, Department of, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Services, Department of - Miscellaneous, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Services, Department of - Capitol Outlay, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General Services, Department of - Real Property Issues, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General Services, Department of - Chesapeake Builders and DMV Lease, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Services, Department of - (DPS Miscellaneous), 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Services, Department of - (DPS Travel Policy), 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General Services, Department of - Division of Risk Management, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Human Rights, Council on, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Information Management, Council on, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Information Management, Council on - VIPNet, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Information Technology, Department of - Miscellaneous, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Information Technology, Department of - Virginia Public Broadcasting Board, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Information Technology, Department of - E-Mail Capabilities, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
  - Local Government, Commission on - Miscellaneous, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Local Government, Commission on - Assessment of Mandates on Local Government, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Personnel and Training, Department of - Miscellaneous, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Personnel and Training, Department of - Combined Virginia Campaign, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Personnel and Training, Department of - Classification and Compensation, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Personnel and Training, Department of - Fair Labor Standards Act, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Personnel and Trainging, Department of - Health Insurance Premium, 1999. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Personnel and Training, Department of - Medical Savings Account, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Personnel and Training, Department of - Virginia Executive Institute and Commonwealth Management Institute, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Veterans Affairs, Department of - Virginia Veterans Care Center, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Veterans Affairs, Department of - Virginia Veterans Cemetery, 1994-1998. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Governor's Working Papers - Miscellaneous, 1994-1996. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Commerce and Trade, Secretary of, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Education, Secretary of, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Education, Secretary of - Higher Education Decentralization, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Health and Human Resources, Secretary of, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Natural Resources, Secretry of, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Natural Resources, Secretry of - Enviromental Impact Reports Approvals, 1994-1997. (Box 2, Folder 5-8)
  - Public Safety, Secretary of, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Transportation, Secretary of, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Liason Office, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Retirement System, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - African Trade Office Trip, 1994. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Commonwealth Competition Council, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Congressional Delegation Briefing, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Decision Brief, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - ESOP, 1997. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Executive Order - Memorandum, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Intellectual Property, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Intellectual Property - Requests from Agencies, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Memorandum to Agency Heads, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Memorandum to Governor's Cabinet, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Memorandum to Governor's Office, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Phone Bill, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Presentation by Michael E. Thomas - Speeches, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Surplus Property, Governor's Commission on, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Travel - General Study, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Travel - Vehicles Study, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Utility Audit, 1994-1998. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Legislative Studies, 1997. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Legislative Studies, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Legislative Studies, 1994-1995. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - General Assembly - Development of Legislation, 1998. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - General Assembly - Regular and Veto Sessions, 1997. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - General Assembly - Review of Agency Submissions, 1996. (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - General Assembly, 1995. (Box 2, Folder 38)